[Music]
Stanford
University okay if we're ready let's go
then we talked last time about angular
momentum operators and I started to show
you how the algebra of the angular
momentum operators Works how
multiplets with different angular
momentum have certain numbers of states
and the
states
form they call
multiplets I'll come back to them in a
minute but let's just talk more
generally about what angular momentum is
about uh a good example is an object a
particle moving in a central force
field here's the center particle moves
around in a central force field uh it
has a radial position and an angular
position the angular position really
means two angles an as athal and a polar
angle so it's a three-dimensional system
and the angular momentum is conserved
the angular momentum is a vector and the
angular momentum always is in the plane
perpendicular to the
motion plane perpendicular to the
orbit so there's the angle angular
momentum the orbit the orbital plane is
perpendicular to it and because the
angular momentum is conserved as a
vector the orbital plane is also
conserved the orbital plane stays the
same but of course the radial position
moves around in a circle not a circle
take it back moves around in some orbit
that's classical that's classical
Quantum mechanically the particle is
described by a wave function
the angular
momentum operator has to do with the
angular dependence of the wave function
in general the wave function in a
situation like this would be a function
of position of course it's always a
function of position could be a function
of X Y and Z but you could also write it
as a function of the radial coordinate
the radial distance and two angles Po
and as AAL
angle we talked a little bit the first
time maybe the first time maybe the last
time I can't remember we talked a little
bit about angular momentum in two
Dimensions let's go back to that for a
moment if everything was in two
dimensions then the angular momentum
would just be the generator of rotations
about uh about the perpendicular axis
here and its structure as a quantum
mechanical operator would just be
angular momentum is equal to Min - I
time the derivative with respect to the
angle that's the analog of momentum
being minus I * derivative with respect
to
position what it tells you is how the
wave function changes with angle so let
me just remind you if you look for
angular momentum igen States then what
you're looking for is functions which
satisfy minus I d by D Theta let's say
functions of R and
Theta in two Dimensions we don't have to
worry about fi just R and
Theta and if we're looking for an igen
Vector of the angular momentum we want
to set that equal to a number the the
igen value L Time s of R in
Theta that's a little differential
equation and it doesn't really depend on
r r is just a spectator here R um
derivative is with respect to Theta so
this is an equation about the Theta
dependence and it doesn't really care
about R we know what the solution of
equations like this is the solution
is
s equals e to the
i l
Theta e to the i l Theta where Theta has
where L has to be an integer an integer
in order that the wave function comes
back to itself when you go around the
closed uh closed
curve well what about the r
dependence what should the r dependence
be this doesn't tell you what the r
dependence is so the answer is you have
an angular momentum igen function no
matter
what let's not use the same function
let's use a different function let's
call Kai
of
R any wave function that looks like e to
the I Theta it doesn't matter what its R
dependence is it will be an angular
momentum IG state so angular momentum
has to do with the angular dependence of
the wave
function the um the radial dependence is
irrelevant to the angular momentum it
may be relevant to the energy but it's
not relevant to the angular momentum and
the same is true in three
dimensions in three dimensions angular
momentum also has to do with the angular
dependence and there are particular wave
functions
generally arbitrary functions of radius
doesn't matter what they are times
specific functions they're usually
called
y of theta and
F which are analogous
to the e to the i l thetas and those
wave functions are the things which
determine the angular momentum of the
state they are the things which change
when you rotate the configuration and
angular momentum has to do with rotating
configurations so when we talked about
angular momentum igen States we were
really talking about these functions of
theta and fi now it's awkward to worry
about Theta and fi we don't have to what
we did last time was we used a bunch of
Tricks so let me go back to those tricks
and remind you but keep in mind at every
stage what we're talking about is the
angular dependence of wave
functions
okay let's uh let's
recall what we learned last time
we started with the angular momentum
operators LZ LX l
y we found out that they have certain
commutation relations LX with l y equal
I
LZ there's H bars in here but I'm not
going to belabor them I don't care about
them right now LX l yal i LZ and cyclic
permutations to more like
it all right then we started to play
some games we played some games because
draak taught us to play those games not
because any of us would have been smart
enough to figure them out ourselves I
don't know maybe we would have who knows
uh but the trick was to construct well
to pick one of the
operators and work in the basis of that
operator in other words pick LZ Z and
work with igen vectors of LZ with igen
value M we don't know off hand what the
spectrum of IG values is
but let's just postulate or let's just
Define the IG values to be Little
M forget for the moment whether they're
integers or not they may or may not be
integers but this defines the igen
vector of LZ with igen value M and we
worked in that basis and we found to our
great joy that the operators LX plus or
minus i l
y which we called L plus or
minus had some nice
properties were
useful
uh I'm not going to write down the
proper properties you have them written
down from last time I
hope they follow the properties follow
it's commutation properties they follow
from the commutation properties of the
L's but here's what we learned we found
out that if we
start with an igen Vector of LZ with
igen value
M and we hit it with
l+ I
guess forgot whether we put the pluses
and minuses upstairs or downstairs
doesn't matter what did that
do that gave us another igen
Vector with n + one we worked out that
was a that was a consequence of the
simple algebra of these commutation
relations we worked it out by
just sticking in the uh sticking in the
equations it was a couple of lines and
we found out that l+ is a raising
operator this is called a raising
operator if this is if this line
represents the spectrum of possible
values of
M is zero so forth this tells us that we
found another igen
Vector which is one unit up it has not
yet told us anything about whether the
M's are integers or not but it tells us
that if we find one we can find another
one
by hitting it with l+ likewise we can
find another one by hitting it with L
[Music]
minus so L pluses and L minuses are
operators which take you up and down the
spectrum of uh of igen values of
LZ okay that was the first thing that we
discovered from the algebra of these
things the next thing we asked was well
does this go on forever and ever and
ever
it will go on forever and ever and ever
unless it comes to an end how can it
come to an end the only way it can come
to an end is If l+ instead of giving
another nonzero igen Vector gives us
zero that's the only way it can come to
an
end and if it does come to an end and
typically they do come to an end if it
does come to an end that's the end of
the spectrum r ing that you get by
raising and let's suppose that's over
here then we have things separated by an
integer but we have one more thing that
we know we know that the z-axis that
there's nothing preferential about the
plus Z
axis if we simply rotated the whole
picture around and replace the plus
z-axis by the minus z-axis all the rules
would be the same
so for that
reason the Spectrum has to be symmetric
about the origin anything you can say
about LZ you can say exactly the same
thing about minus LZ because they just
related by
rotation so if the Spectrum ends at some
point
here it has to
end going downward at exactly the same
point except
reflected now each action of l+ minus
displaces You by an integer how is it
possible to come to an end with the ends
being symmetric like this if they have
to be integers for example if this point
was at 3/4 here and you kept going down
down down down down you would never come
to minus
3/4 is that right yeah you you'd never
come to uh yes you'd never come to minus
3/4 the only way that it can happen that
you can end and be symmetric is if you
start at an integer that's one
possibility let's say this is integer
two here and then end at minus 2 that's
one possibility and the only other
possibility is that you start at a half
integer for example the simplest
case would
be that the Spectrum ends at a
half and ends in the other direction at
minus a
half that's still separated by an
integer in that case l+ would take you
from the Lower State to the Upper
State L minus would take you from the
upper state to the Lower
State but what would happen if l+ hit
the upper
state would give zero if L minus hits
the Lower State it would give zero so
that's the way we know what the spectrum
of the angular momenta is the spectrum
is either integers or half
integers and each collection of States
like this if it ends it ends at some
highest
point which is usually called let's
forget the half IND case the half
integer case will come back to us but
not uh probably not
tonight let's take the integer
case all right
could end over here here
zero 1 2 3 1 two 3 and over here so
there'd be how many states 1 2 3 4 5 six
seven states here seven possible
States the highest state has the maximum
value of M before it's killed by the
next action of the operator the maximum
value of M is called l
l equals the maximum value of M for that
particular collection of States minus L
is of course the minimum
value of
M and so the values of M go from minus L
to plus
L and then nothing beyond that from
above nothing Beyond it from below how
many states is that Al together if you
go from minus L to plus L 2 L +
1 okay so a multiplet a collection of
States uh is characterized which which
um with a given value
of well we'll see what they have a given
value of but a collection of states of
this type A
multiplet has typically two l+ one
States 2 L +1
States that's the first thing we
find number could have it that's the
other sure that's just L equals infinity
right that is it is a possibility but
uh
um it's uh not one that we're going to
worry about the
pathological there isn't a
pathological for a variety of reasons
the number a lot of the reasons that
they're pathological but among other
things energy usually P depends on the
angular momentum as you increase the
angular momentum keeping other things
fixed the energy goes
up and
um uh if you're interested in states of
fin energy then you're not interested in
states with infinite angular
momentum
okay let's do one more little
exercise what characterizes these
multiplets well I'll tell you what
characterizes these multiplets it's the
magnitude of the angular
momentum all of the states in this 2 L +
1 collection have the same value of the
magnitude of the angular momentum now
what do we mean by the magnitude of the
angular momentum what we mean by the
magnitude of the angular momentum is
exactly what you would mean in classical
physics or I should say the square of
the magnitude of the angular momentum
it's the
magnitude of the angular momentum Vector
squared and that's equal to lx2 + L y^ 2
+ LZ
squared the only difference between
classical physics and quantum physics is
these are now operators they're not just
numbers in the usual sense they're
quantum mechanical operators and let's
see what we can find
out about l s in particular l s for a
multiplet of 2 L + one States in other
words supposing we have a multiplet
which terminates from above at L
terminates From Below at minus L what
can we say about its l s okay so here's
the tricks and they're all tricks but
they're nice
tricks this is equal to
lz2 now first
classical lx2 + L y^ 2 that's plus LX +
i l y do I want that no I want LX minus
i
y time LX + i
y this is lx2 + L Y and the cross term
zero
classically so this is a correct
equation classically it's not quite
right Quantum mechanically and the
reason is that LX and l y don't
commute we actually have an extra term
here we have the extra term let's see
what it is it's I LX l y That's this
product and then minus i l y LX so it
has the commutator of LX l y in it sorry
the Comm
of LX and l
y
yeah in other words we've overshot by
writing in LX - i l y * LX + i y we have
to subtract
this minus
I commutator LX l
y that's just the extra piece that's
there because LX * l y Y is not equal to
l y * LX okay so that's
straightforward but what is the
commutator of LX with l
y LX with l y is I
LZ
so this is equal to LZ
2 now we're going to get an I from the
LZ there's an I here and then there's
another I from the commutator I * - I is
Plus + 1 so this will give me plus
LZ LZ 2 plus LZ and then we have
plus lus *
l+ okay you with
me that's l
s the square of the angular
momentum now let's apply that let's take
this operator and apply
it to the maximum highest M
State m equal l m =
l so let's take this
L2
on
l l is the highest state there okay what
do we get
we get lz2 on
L plus
LZ time
L plus L minus
l+ time
L okay first of all what is this script
L here it's an igen Vector remember what
it stands for it stands for the igen
vector of LZ with the highest possible
value in this
multiplet what is LZ LZ is equal to
little
l in the state up here LZ is equal to
little L let just go back a
minute too many letters I'm sorry if
there so many letters but uh that's just
the way it is
LZ or the state M was defined to be an
igen Vector of LZ that's what this says
in particular the top IG Vector here we
can just substitute for M we substitute
l so here we have it LZ on L is just the
numerical number L on
L what about LZ
squ it's just L squ you're just hitting
it with the operator LZ twice the first
time you hit it it gives you an L the
second time you hit it it gives you
another l so that's l s
okay that was easy but what about this
here guy what are we going to do about
it it's zero why because
l+ when it hits the top runs out of
states that was the definition of the
top here the definition of the top state
is that l+ gives
zero so we can just erase
this and now we've learned something
that this state L is an igen
Vector of the square of the angular
momentum let's write it this way let's
write it down l^2 +
L time l or better yet L * L + 1
just to remind you where it came from an
l s came from here and an L came from
here l^2 + L is L * L + 1 so what do we
find we find out
that the states in this multiplet here
the top state there the top the highest
state there has an igen value of
l^2 which is L * L + 1
the square of the angular momentum for
that state is not little L squar it's
almost just little L squar there's a
little Quantum correction here if we
were doing classical
mechanics we would expect that the
square of the angular momentum would
just be the square of the uh of the
angular momentum about the z-axis for
the top state there incidentally the
highest state is like the state rotating
about the z-axis where all of the
angular momentum is in the vertical
Direction that's why it has the highest
value in the other direction it would be
smaller okay so we find a little
surprise it's not just L2 it's l * L + 1
but then there's another surprise and
this is something this is a nice little
exercise for you to do yourself it's
very easy but I'll let you work it out
yourself every one of these states in
this same multiplet have exactly the
same value of l s
they all have the same magnitude for the
square of the angular momentum basically
what this multiplet is is it's a quantum
mechanical version of a state with a
given angular momentum except in any
possible
Direction they all have the same L
squared the same square of the angular
momentum but they have different
projections onto the
z-axis what's new in quantum mechanics
is that the projection onto the z-axis
is quantized
comes in integer
multiples okay so
that's that's what we know about angular
momentum question yeah um could you
state a little bit more I didn't I don't
understand the words that you said in
terms of the little exercise where you
do oh okay
good yeah here's the
exercise
okay let's good
what we've shown is that
l^2 on the maximum igen
Vector is equal to l * L
+1 on l in other words
that this IG Vector here happens also to
be an igen Vector of the square of the
angular momentum next step I would like
to
show that L
-1 also equals L * L
+1 * l
minus1 in other words that the next
state down has exactly the same value
for l
s okay how do you do that well you say
start with
L2 and now hit this with L minus on l
L
minus on L is the state L minus one and
we want to prove that's that that that's
equal to l * L +
1 * l
- on
L that's the thing you want to
prove
okay can any body guess how to prove
it does the algebra here suggest
anything I'll tell you what it suggests
to me it suggests to me that we figure
out what the commutator of L2 with L
minus
is imagine we
discovered imagine we discovered a
marvelous fact which I'm not telling you
is
true it's true
though that L2 and L minus commute
supposing we discovered
that then I could say that this was also
equal we're trying to prove this
relationship I would then say that this
is equal to l
minus * L 2 L
right but what's l s on
L line on the
let's see what do we want to do here
um if this commutes with this we can
push this through
here that's then equal to l * L +
1 yeah we would have proved this
relationship we would have proved this
relationship we would have proved that
this is equal to L minus * L * L +
1 L which is exactly what this
says so if we can prove that l^2
commutes with L
minus then we can
prove that the state L + one is also an
igen Vector of l^2 what about L minus 2
what about the next state down same
thing we just go down till we run out of
states
[Music]
um here's the okay here's the exercise
the exercise is to prove that l s
commutes with any one of the components
of angular momentum let's call it l
subi LX l y l
l0 if it commutes with any of the
components then it will certainly
commute with l+ and L minus L plus and L
minus is just LX Plus I plus orus i l y
so there's an exercise prove that L2
commutes with any one of the
L's
um all right so here's what we found
from the things that I showed you plus
the little exercise that you can do
yourself is that when you find a
multiplet like
this going from L to minus L such that
there's no more above it and no more
below it you found not only igen vectors
of
LZ igen vectors for which LZ is equal to
M but you've also found igen vectors of
the square of the angular momentum with
igen value L * L +
1 where L is just the maximum value of
n so
for each one of these little L's there
are two l+ one States and they all have
the same squared angular
momentum roughly speaking they have the
same squared angular momentum because
they just tilted tilts away from the
vertical axis that's a rough statement
that's Quantum mechanically it's a
little trickier than that but that's the
classical analog that uh that by
rotating and changing the Z component of
the angular momentum you haven't changed
l
s okay so that's what we know about
angular momentum multipet yeah um can
you raise the board uh to show your uh
factorization so when you factor lx2
plus L y^2 you could have just as fairly
gotten L plus L minus as the
operator and then I would have had the
opposite sign
here yeah it would it would have given
you exactly the same thing if you had
the L if you had the L minus to the
right you would want to hit it on the
lowest State instead of the highest
state but the sign of this would change
it would all work out all work out the
same way it's a good question
but
uh okay so what we found is that there
are collections of functions of the
angles these igen vectors are
functions they're functions of the
angles why because rotation only it
affects the angular
dependence their functions and what what
characterizes
them a value of M the igen vector of
LZ so whatever they are they functions
which have a little subscript
M and that's the component but they also
have they're also igen vectors of l s or
in other words they can be characterized
by a little
L and they're called y LM and their
functions of theta and
F you know what these things are
called y LMS of theta and
F spherical harmonics
they're functions on a unit sphere
functions of theta and F and they're the
analoges on the sphere of e to the plus
or minus I
Theta i i
l i l
Theta they're the threedimensional
analoges this is the two dimensional
functions strictly speaking these are
functions on a circle so they're
onedimensional functions but think of of
them as functions for a two-dimensional
problem these are the corresponding
functions for the three-dimensional
problem and we don't really care very
much about exactly what they are we're
going to finesse exactly what they are
we're never going to really need it we
could figure out what these functions
are but we don't never going to need it
all we ever have to really know is that
for every little value of L there are 2
l+ one of
them the 2 L plus one of them have
magnetic quantum numbers M that range
from 0 to L and to minus
L and that the square of the angular
momentum is L * L + 1 that's all we're
ever going to have to really
know
um to do atomic
physics okay any questions about the
structure of angular momentum multiplets
and they all have the same energy they
all have the same energy and the reason
is because the angular momentum commutes
with the
hamiltonian that means when you when you
apply L to a function it doesn't change
the uh the energy so they all have the
same
energy at least for a problem of a
central
Force for Central Force the angular
momentum commutes with a hamiltonian and
that's enough to prove that all of these
have the same
energy
okay no questions we'll move
on in fact let's move now to the central
Force problem now I'm going I'm not
going to take you through all of the
manipulations involving partial
derivatives all over the place with
respect to Theta and fi and so forth
we're going to do this by using a little
bit of intuition from classical
physics and and work out with a a tiny
bit of cheating the cheating is going to
be to use classical physics to make a
guess or two but the guesses are well
motivated and we can um we can do this
rigorously what is what we want to do we
want to solve the Schrodinger equation
for a problem with a
hamiltonian which is p ^2 over 2 m now P
stands for the three components of of of
momentum so it's a vector P ^2 over 2m
kinetic energy plus some potential
energy which only depends on the
radius Central Force
problem later we'll be specific about
what central Force problem of course
what we're going to think about is a
kulum
force uh but for the moment let's not uh
let's not specialize
and let's do classical physics
first okay first
statement the angular momentum is
conserved now you could check it you
could work it out by working out the
equations of motion and seeing that the
angular momentum is conserved you can
also just say angular momentum is
conserved whenever you have rotational
symmetry and that's correct the same
statement is saying that you have
momentum cons ation whenever you have
translation invariants it's n's theorem
classically
Quant heavy heavy
scone that's a good scone man
all right so let's believe angular
momentum is
conserved angular momentum is a vector
oops excuse me R cross p
it's conserved that means its magnitude
is conserved but also its direction is
conserved and that means as I said
before that the plane of the
orbit is also conserved so once we know
the plane of the orbit is also conserved
and that everything is rotationally
symmetric we might as well classically
put this whole thing in in the XY
plane so there's our orbit orbits do not
have to be
circles most orbits are not circles in
fact for a general problem most orbits
won't even be
closed if you take a general potential
most orbits will not be
closed they
will they will process about um the axis
of the orbit will
process we're not going to worry too
much about whether the orbits are closed
it's not our concern right
now now
next let's look
at an orbit here's
R and let's put the momentum over here
the momentum is along some direction
it's in the plane because we because we
know that the motion is in a plane so so
it's in the plane and it's pointing in
some direction it may or may not be
perpendicular to R in fact it could even
be um the velocity could be a long R
there are Orbits for example which just
go back and forth through the
origin uh so there's no rule that says
that the momentum is perpendicular to R
there is a rule that says the angular
momentum is perpendicular to both R and
momentum but that's we're finished with
that okay let's take the the uh the
momentum vector
and decompose
it into a angular part let's call it the
Theta component P Theta and a r
component so the momentum has two
components one along the angular
Direction and One along the r
Direction what about p^
s p^ s is the sum of the squares of both
of them so H is p r
2 plus P Theta 2 / 2
m and that's it but what about the
angular momentum the magnitude of the
angular momentum is p Theta * R is that
clear to you that P Theta * R is the
angular momentum R cross
p r cross P the magnitude of it is the
magnitude of R times the magnitude of P
Theta so the magnitude of the angular
momentum is equal to P
Theta * R
everybody
magnitude P Theta time
r or another way to write
it is that L first of all
L2 is equal to P Theta 2 * R
2 and now let's
write P Theta 2 is l^2 over R
2 that was
easy and let's stick it into the
hamiltonian p r^ 2 plus P oh this is not
I I'm sorry you didn't correct me plus v
of
R okay p r s well that's just PR r
s
h is p r
2 over 2
m but what about P Theta squar P Theta
squ is
l^2 / R
2 plus v of r
let's erase all of this
now look at what we have we have a
problem which for all practical purposes
could be thought of as a problem in one
dimension namely the radial Direction PR
S Plus a potential energy V of r plus
another term in the potential energy
remember that L is
conserved so once you pick l once you
know what the angular momentum is it
doesn't change on you so once you know
what it is you can freeze it and you can
say the hamiltonian of this system is
just p r 2 as though it was just a
one-dimensional problem plus an extra
term which goes like 1 / r
squared plus the original V of R what is
this term called
physically what is
it is it is it attractive or is it
repulsive how do you tell whether it's
attractive or
repulsive it's
attractive why do you think it's
attractive potential
energy one of R squ gets bigger As you
move
away so sorry r Square gets bigger As
you move away 1 / R 2 decreases as you
move away so which way is this Force
pushing
you forces push you towards smaller
energy forces always push you toward
smaller energy that's why they're minus
the derivative of the potential with
respect to
position this is pushing you away from
the origin what kind of thing is this
pushing you away from the origin there
was nothing in this problem that pushed
you away from the origin what is it
yeah sure it's centrifugal
force or this is the potential energy
that's associated with a centrifugal
force and it gets very big when R gets
small when R gets small for fixed
angular momentum for fixed angular
momentum it really repels you away from
the origin and so if an object comes in
with a given amount of angular momentum
it can't get very close to the origin
what it does is swing around the
origin okay so this is what keeps the
particle from getting to the
origin and it is the centrifical force
there's only one situation where it's
not there when is it not
there for l equals 0 right for l equals
0 and then for l equals 0 we're talking
about an orbit which just goes through
the origin back and forth and back and
forth through the origin it has no
angular momentum
and this term isn't
there but as long as there's any angular
momentum then it can't get to the origin
because there's this huge repulsion
effect it's not a real repulsion it's
the centrifugal force but it's
there P of R what about P of R that's
just the momentum associated with the r
Direction okay
let's go one one a little more a little
bit more with a classical physics let's
plot this effective potential energy
this becomes the effective potential
energy for the one-dimensional
problem it has the ordinary potential
energy plus the centrifugal barrier this
is called the centrifugal barrier and it
looks like
this let's suppose V of R is attractive
for example it could be the attraction
the electron to the
proton
uh then V of R would look something like
that let's do it a little
better V of
R would be negative because it's ATT
traction and it would be 1 / R so it
would look something like this now what
of that's V of
R what about l^2 over R 2 well the
depending on L whether or not for any L
except l equals z it's going to blow up
at the
origin like 1 / R 2 and then fall
quickly to
zero in fact if V of R is the
potential it goes like 1 / R it falls
more slowly than the centrifugal barrier
centrifugal barrier Falls very quickly
to zero 1/ R 2 and V over r a little
more slowly what does the combination of
them look like
well the combination of them which is
dominant at small R for small R which
one is
bigger 1 / r s or 1/
r 1 r s is much bigger so uh very close
to the origin this is the dominant thing
what about for large R if V is 1 / r
supposing v is the coolon
potential 1 / R is bigger than 1 / r s
so ASM totically far out the Kone
potential wins and what happens in
between what happens in between looks
like
this
now okay so what kind of motions do you
have we have an effective problem which
is completely one-dimensional now it
only depends on the r
axis and all of the angular story is
fixed by the angular momentum so once
you know the angular momentum it becomes
a one-dimensional problem what do you
think Motion in this kind of potential
looks
like well the simplest kind of orbit or
the simplest kind of motion would just
be
equilibrium down at the bottom of the
potential that's an orbit in which R
doesn't change it's a circular
orbit okay that's a circular orbit what
other kind of orbits can you have well
what other kind of motions could you
have in a potential which looks like
this basically you can have oscillations
back and
forth oscillations which go back and
forth take the particle from a minimum
distance from the origin to a maximum
and back again so these are orbits which
go from a minimum distance to a maximum
distance and back again for the Kum
potential they would be the elliptical
orbits
and that's the classical physics in a
nutshell that's the classical
physics what about the quantum
physics for the quantum physics we have
a wave
function the wave function instead of we
don't have a particle position we don't
have a momentum we have a wave function
and the wave
function is s of R and also
angles but the angular structure
structure is totally taken into account
by knowing the angular momentum if we
know the angular momentum then we know
that the angular part of the wave
function is just one of these spherical
harmonics which I've erased but
uh that's
gone but we don't have to worry about it
it's a one-dimensional problem
s of R and what does it satisfy it
satisfies the shring or equation that h
on S of R let's say the time independent
shinger equation what is the time
independent shringer equation what do
you put on the right hand side the
energy and it determines the igen values
and the IG vectors of energy now what is
h h begins with PR squar what is PR
PR R is of course I D
bydr as always in quantum mechanics a
component of the momentum is I bar time
derivative with respect to the the
corresponding
coordinate so p s here's PR s PR s is
going to
equal minus because of two factors of i
h bar squ I'm putting in the H bars now
second derivative with respect to
R that's the first term in the
hamiltonian I I left something out I
left out twice the
mass whose Mass might I be talking about
incidentally the planet
Mercury more likely the electron for
this discussion but it could be the
planet Mercury
2 I don't think we would bother doing
quantum mechanics then D2 by D r^
2 that's the first term in the
hamiltonian the second term in the
hamiltonian is exactly what's written
there plus 1/ 2
m L2 over R 2 but what is l s now we
come back to
here L2 is not little l s it's l * L + 1
why because this is the square of the
angular momentum what appeared there was
the square was lx2 + L Y2 +
lz2 and so this becomes
L * L + 1/ r
2 that's one of the effects of quantum
mechanics just to change L2 to L * L +
1 and finally plus v of r
R and you can plug in your favorite
potential into there what do we do with
it we act on S and S is now a function
of r s of
r s of
R equals e s of R and that's our
Schrodinger equation the solutions of
equation are the igen vectors of energy
with given angular momentum and um the
igen values are the energy
levels I have a feeling I left out some
H squares in
here um I probably did because where did
it come from it came from P Theta
squared it's probably an H bar squar in
here too
if you track
it I think yeah
yes all right that's what we would like
to solve we'd like to solve this find
the energy levels of an atom we would
like to find the wave functions of an
atom we'd like to know what the electron
probability distribution is
like and so forth okay so we're not
going to do that we're not going to do
it because it's just a matter of solving
different IAL equations and this is not
a course in differential equations but
we can still sort of scout it out
and yeah for a given L
MH I
think again all the vales the same
energy Lev yeah all of all of those all
of these levels here the 2 L plus one
them have the same value of little L and
therefore the same energy oh okay
yeah so you were able to
replace
um l s with l l +1 because s is a linear
combination of the
M's
this but that applies to any value of
L we said right yeah so if we know the
angular momentum if we know the angular
momentum quantum number of the wave
function then we can plug it in what L
is really the maximum value it's the
maximum mean value for that
multiple yeah there are wave functions
of any angular momentum but they come in
these and the pattern is that they come
in these 2 L +1
multiplets the 2 l+1 one multiplets are
the quantum mechanical analog of if you
find a wave function and you rotate it
around
right this tells you what the energy
levels are associated with a given LR
and now you want to solve it okay too
hard to solve for most
potentials most potentials you write
down you'd have to solve it
numerically the coolum potential happens
to be solvable
if you want to solve
it the solutions to this equation are
called Gigan b pols or Gigan B functions
good luck look up Gigan B functions you
we learn very little from
it I used to know what a gig and B about
polinomial is I do not
anymore okay let's look at the at the
effective potential what we're doing is
we're solving the Schrodinger equation
in a potential which looks like this
we're solving the Schrodinger
equation for a problem which effectively
has a potential energy which looks like
this and we want to know what kind of
wave functions and what kind of energy
levels will it
be
okay if you know anything about solving
Schrodinger
equations then
you know that given L with given l in
other words with given the potential you
know that first of all typically there
are more than one bound State a bound
state is a state which is confined with
a wave function which doesn't leak out
too
far they correspond to discrete energy
levels and you know that the thing which
characterizes the energy level is the
number of nodes in the wave function
does everybody know what a node
is a wave function which pass which
doesn't which is never zero let's say
it's always positive has no nodes if it
goes up goes down passes through the
origin and then it has one node so here
are some functions with different
numbers of nodes here's
oops here's a function with no
nodes here's a function with one node
how about a function with two
nodes a function with two nodes goes up
comes down goes back up and comes back
down the number of nodes are what
characterize the different energy levels
of a solution to the Schrodinger
equation the more nodes the higher the
energy why do why would it be that the
more nodes the higher the
energy what's that yeah
something like that yeah the more nodes
the faster it Wiggles the faster it
Wiggles the the large of the
momentum momentum is characterized by
Wiggles the wave functions of momentum
States wiggle the higher the momentum
the faster they wiggle the more they
wiggle the more nodes they're going to
have so generally speaking it's a
theorem it's actually not it's a theorem
the lowest energy state in the given
potential has no nodes the first excited
state has one node the next excited
state has two nodes eventually you may
or may not run out of um of solutions
but they're ordered according to the
number of
nodes so let's start let's see now what
we can say about the the
spectrum of an
atom it doesn't have to be a realistic
atom this could be an atom with uh one
over R potential like a realistic atom
it could be 1/ root of R it could be uh
e to Theus R but some potential what can
we say let's see if we can
organize the energy levels and the
states of the
atom okay let's see how I did
this yeah let's plot
horizontally the different angular
momenta
the little L's little L L equal
0 L =
1 L = 2 L = 3 and so forth now each one
of these L's has its own Schrodinger
equation remember the Schrodinger
equation involves L as a parameter
so each L may have several bound
States several
Solutions let's take L equal 0 L equals
0 will have a lowest energy State let's
see what are we plotting here let's plot
energy energy
vertically okay there'll be the lowest
energy level it has no nodes and L
equals zero so it's someplace over
here okay what's the next state with L
equals 0 the next state with L equals 0
has a node in it same potential one node
so it's up here over
somewhere how many states are there for
every for for l equals z each wave each
case has one state L * L + 1 is 1 when L
is equal to zero is that right
no no no no 2 L + 1 is
a 2 L
2 L 2 L + one is uh right 2 L + 1 is one
so every one of the states with L equals
z one node two nodes three nodes and
four node they all have one state
associated with them and they there some
they're not equally spaced they are
whatever they
are whatever they
are
okay those are the energy levels with
zero angular momentum
now let's go to angular momentum
one at angular momentum 1 there is also
a state with one with no nodes we solve
the same Schrodinger equation except
with Lal 1
here L * L + 1 when L is equal to 1 1 *
2 is 2 right 1 * 2 is 2 on the other
hand for L equal 0 this was
Zero okay so same Shing equation
different value of L at Lal 1 we will
also find things with one node will
their energy be larger or smaller than
the L equals z state with no l with no
node just a wild
guess yeah it's got angular momentum
it's you know it's swinging around there
it's got angular momentum and besides
which this is a positive term in the
hamiltonian so how could it possibly
lower the energy and it can't so the L
equals one state with no nodes
will lie somewhat
above the the corresponding state with L
equals
likewise the K the state with two
nodes this one lies above this one will
lie above this one
and just by virtue the whole Spectrum
may move
over but it will move up a little bit
because the angular momentum is
higher how many St are there at each one
of these levels I've drawn a little Dash
here to indicate a possible energy level
a an energy level but what is its
degeneracy how many states are there at
each one of those
dashes 2 L + 1 three so we should really
draw these as three little
dashes if I was trying to separate them
and indicate
three
states each one of these is a
triplet okay what about at L equals 2 at
L equals 2 we' put in a little more
angular momentum surely we've raised the
energy again and in fact we will have
how many states will there be for each
state at Lal
2 five 2 L + 1 so when we go up to L
equal 2 let's move them over a little
bit L equal 2 we will have go up a
little bit and we'll have five
states 1 2 3 4 5 1 2 3 4 5 and so it
goes Lal
3 2 L + 1 let's see 3 * 6 seven states
and so
forth and that's about what it looks
like that's about what the general
solution looks like for sort of
arbitrary potential at some point when
the energy gets too
high just like in classical physics what
happens when the energy gets too high
for an orbit around the
sun es it Escape it exceeds ESC escape
velocity and it's no longer bound to the
uh to the
sun likewise when the energy gets too
high the electron escapes and so there's
a bound a bound to the energy up
here no States above there are actually
bound so all about states have basically
negative energy the Energy starts it
should be goes negative down here and
this is what the spectrum of a of
anything an entral Force looks
like the Kum potential has a very
special feature it's almost accidental
it's not exact it is an exact statement
about the non-relativistic kulum
potential but it is not an exact
statement about atoms the statement I'm
going to tell you it's violating by
every possible correction to the uh to
the simplest theory of the
atom uh it's a violated by the finite
size of the nucleus it's violated by
relativistic Corrections it's violated
by the fact that the electron has a spin
which couples to the or everything in on
Earth violates it so it's something of
an
accident it's very special to the kulum
force and it goes as follows
the first level here which has moved up
a little bit this is the zero node State
the zero node state for l equals 1
happens to be have exactly the same
energy as the one node state for l
equals
z here's the one node state for l equals
0 the zero node state the first one that
occurs for Lal 1 occurs at exactly the
same energy as the one node state for l
equals z that's a
mouthful what about the two node State
the two node the
sorry the one node state of L equals 1
occurs at the same energy as the two
node state of L equals z exactly the
same uh exactly the same for the simple
kulum force and so on and so forth this
is a
pattern now you go to Lal
2 the Lal 2 zero node state in other
words the lowest L equal 2 state has
exactly the same energy as which is this
now this
is this is no node one node two nodes
it's up here and there are five
states 1 2 3 four five what about the
lals 3 the Lal 3 begins up here seven
states 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and so
forth that's the pattern and it's an
accident it's not completely an accident
nothing in mathematics is ever an
accident but you can say things are
accidental when you know just small
changes in the potential or small
changes in anything uh ruin it and this
in that sense is an accident I'm not
going to uh
I'm not going to prove it it sounds like
an extra symmetry law it sounds like
extra
degeneracy it sounds like there
degeneracies between states uh it it is
a symmetry but it's a rather bizarre one
it's a rather bizarre one that you would
never notice if you were thinking about
this as I said it's very special to the
kolom potential and is not exact so I
think we won't bother proving it it's a
nuisance to
prove um
but it is a fact it's a very special
fact about the special one over R
potential so there it is that's the
Spectrum what is the degener the
degeneracy the degeneracy at each level
here's the lowest energy level there's
only one state it has angular momentum
zero it's called the ground state it's
the lowest energy state of the atom If
This Were the hydrogen atom for example
it will be the most deeply bound State
then you go up one level you go to the
first node of the zero angular momentum
state or no nodes for the angular
momentum and how many states do you
get this is
one this is four how about the next one
up 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 nine nine states at
the next
level anybody want to guess what the
next one
is 16 is
right so for the coom potential for the
coom potential the states of the
generate like this and the degeneracy is
always the square of some integer you
say you
mean the atom approxim the hydrogen atom
approximately satisfies
this uh it's a very good
approximation but all kinds of things
violate it relativistic
Corrections and as I said just the
finite size of the nucleus is enough to
disturb this now the nucleus is very
very small why does the finite size of
the nucleus disturb it the F the nucleus
is a little ball of charge we've
pretended the charge was a point at the
center okay that would give us exactly
the coolum potential if the charge would
distributed over a little ball the
potential energy would be slightly
different than the exact Kum especially
when you get into the
nucleus the electron can pass through
the nucleus it's just a ball of charge
the nucleus is just a ball of
charge the electron is repelled uh sorry
it's it's attracted to the to the
nucleus and it can pass through the
nucleus when it passes through the
nucleus it senses the fact that the
charge distribution is not the perfect
1/ R Square 1 over R
potential if the potential is anything
but 1 / R this degeneracy
fails so because the nucleus has a
finite size there's a very very slight
deviation away from this now the nucleus
is 100,000 times smaller than the size
of the atomic wave functions so the
nucleus is very small and this is a very
negligible effect but the only point is
just that this is something of an
accident and not particularly deep I
don't know anything deep about it uh the
fact that it has this kind of degeneracy
and that's your spectrum of the hydrogen
atom that's the spectrum of the hydrogen
atom in the idealized approximation
non-relativistic perfect kulum
potential
okay one state
the ground
state four states above
it nine states above
that is that the way real atoms work no
it's not the way real atoms work real
atoms have two degenerate ground States
eight first excited
States
18 next excited
States 32 next excited States
and so there's something missing in this
analysis by a factor of
two spin yeah spin right so we haven't
talked about
spin and I think we won't
tonight
that's all of this is of course just
trickery for
solving the Schrodinger equation let me
write the schinger equation in its
original form form before we went to
angular
variables it wouldn't be particularly
helpful to try to solve it but we might
just try to work to write it
down p^2 means px^ 2 + p y^2 + pz2 it
can also mean p r 2 + P Theta squ but it
means px2 plus py so this really means
minus what is it HR
squar D2 with respect to x^2 plus D2
with respect to y^2 plus D2 with respect
to
z^2 of
S Plus V of R * s equal
e that's the equation we really set out
to
solve solve it by going first to Polar
coordinates or radial coordinates radial
and Ang angular coordinates and then
using the algebra of the angular
momentum to deal with the angular parts
of it and it's very simple the angular
parts of it are all subsumed by saying
you work with angular momentum igen
States L2 is the thing that comes in and
L2 is nothing but L * L +
1 by that time you're down to a
one-dimensional schinger
equation and you use whatever
mathematical uh strategy you know for
solving such
things once you get it down to one
Direction it's just an ordinary
differential equation it's not even a
partial differential equation you only
have derivatives with respect to R
so
so at worst it's it's a numerical
problem question yeah first is the
difference between the idealized SCH law
what you measure is is that could that
be a way of determining the size of the
nucleus no no there are too many crap uh
Corrections which are much
bigger no I just point out the the
nuclear size because it's an easy one to
think about but it's it's minuscule no
the second question is you get back to
the very beginning between classical
mechanics and quantum mechanics the
biggest difference is capital l s is
equal to little l s in
clal and it's equal to L * l- Quantum
what's what's capital Lal little L
little L +
1 right no right Big L S is L * L + 1
yeah
yeah I just said it wrong yeah um and
that difference is caused by the fact
that the things don't commute yeah mhm
it's in other words it's a little
Quantum correction okay right question
right it's a little Quantum
correction yeah yeah do wave functions
have compa
support no no they're spread but they
but they fall off very rapidly As you
move away from uh compact support would
literally mean they go to zero outside a
certain
distance statement that the wave
function as compact support would mean
that it's zero out past a certain point
but it's exponentially small they did
they decrease exponentially so for
practical purposes if you go out sort of
past a certain distance each wave
function becomes negligibly small does
that answer your question yeah but there
is some nonzero probability find
something arbitrarily far away but it
goes to zero exponentially with distance
right question yeah um when L is zero
little L yeah um the shape is not like
this it's just the cool potential right
oh yeah yeah yeah yeah good that's right
when L that that's right when L is zero
then there's no centrifugal
barrier right so what is the meaning of
the stable point in this case you mean
you mean the point at the origin no
before it was in this well okay now the
well is gone yeah that's right that's
right so classically it would just go to
the
center it would just go to the center
and sit at the center
Quantum mechanically it can't both sit
at the center and it would go to the
center not only go to the center but it
would be at rest at the
center the the state of lowest energy
would be at the center where it would
have Nega negative Infinite Energy you
would lower the potential energy by
getting to the center and you would
lower the potential energy by making the
momentum zero you can't have both you
can't have the momentum and the position
definite there's a compromise in
compromise is for the wave function to
have a little bit of spread away from
the origin
here the the the Schrodinger equation
has a solution and the solution has some
sort of exponential um exponential tail
but it's concentrated near the
center it's the uncertainty principle
which prevents it from sitting literally
at the
center yeah yeah you motivated your
classical mechanics yeah yeah we
certainly did was that the trick you
used to make
for lack
ofer no no no
I okay this is motivated by classical
mechanics up to
here
okay but classical mechanics motivated
p^2 over 2 m where P was a vector
and allowed us to write this down once
we write this down we have a very very
precise quantum mechanical problem an
exact Schrodinger
equation
um I did a little bit of guesswork in
going from here to here classically it's
completely rigorous to go from PX s+ p
y^ s+ pz s to go to p r s + P Theta 2
you have to justify uh the step Quantum
mechanically all right but that's that's
something would take an hour at the
Blackboard and you wouldn't learn very
much from it another question if I made
please uh you have Z there which implies
three dimension but you said you reduced
it to two
Dimensions by going only R
Anda um classically
classically
classically Quantum mechanically the
wave function fills up three dimensions
every wave function fills up three
dimensions
classically and the trick is to say
angular momentum is
conserved that means the plane of the
orbit is conserved just change
coordinates so your XY plane is in the
plane of the um of the orbit can't do
that Quantum
mechanically but you did no I
didn't no I didn't
but the fact that you can't do it
believe it or not is just the statement
that l s is replaced by L * L + 1 yeah
it's it's these other lxs and Lys
creeping into
uh yeah if you could just put in for l s
LZ
s then it would just be little l s the
fact that it's three-dimensional comes
back at you just from the L * L + one
yeah
this is more I think what you'll do with
the harmonic OS is there always a
raising and lowering operator looking no
only when you're very
lucky and uh I would say basically
physics has been lucky this way
twice but however the harmonic
oscillator piece of luck is very
pervasive almost everything in nature
can be well approximate or many things
in nature can be approximated by
harmonic oscillators
for example even the
um go not l equals z but go to the
higher angular momentum States and the
higher angular momentum States the
potential looks like
this and there are orbits which
oscillate back and forth at the bottom
here and the simplest approximation to
those orbits is to treat them as a
harmonic oscillator so there's all kinds
of places where are harmonic oscillators
and because of that the trick of
whatever trick whatever trickery goes
into the harmonic oscillator is very
pervasive but uh there are not many
mathematical cases where raising and
lowering operators or sometimes they
call lad
operators only when you're very
lucky
um okay uh that uh that that does it
for atoms for the moment we're going to
come back to atoms we're going to talk
about spin we're going to talk about the
fact that the electron is a fon instead
of a boson and how that determines
atomic structure a little
bit
uh and how atoms radiate and give off
photons all that stuff will come back
to but let's forget atoms for the time
being and come to the harmonic
oscillator
I said everything in physics which has
an equilibrium if you disturb the
equilibrium a little bit chances are
it's going to behave like a harmonic
oscillator so it's a very pervasive
thing and the model for
it is just a particle or a weight on the
end of a
spring
um we're going to simplify it a little
bit some of the parameters aren't
terribly important we imagine a
weight hanging by a
spring it has an equilibrium position
and the deviation from the equilibrium
position not the deviation from the from
where it's hanging but the deviation
from the equilibrium position we'll call
that
X I'm going to take the mass of the
weight to be one
now we can redo it for other masses it
doesn't uh it's a little exercise to do
it uh but uh you won't there's nothing
new nothing new happens so the mass is
one and the spring
constant the spring
constant k k is a standard terminology
for a spring constant will call Omega
squared we're going to find out in a
moment that Omega is the frequency of
oscillation
okay but the spring constant is Omega
squar what is the energy of a classical
oscillator the energy or let's call it
let's give it its name the the
hamiltonian the
hamiltonian is the usual P squ now p is
onedimensional
it's just the momentum the X momentum P
^2 over 2 m that means p t^2 /
2 m has been set equal to 1 plus
K Omega 2 x^2 /
2 let's work out let's just check that
this is right what we're going to do is
work out the Hamilton equations of
motion if you don't remember Hamilton's
equations of motion it's okay I'll tell
you Hamilton
Hamilton's equations of motion are DH by
D DP equals x dot and d h by DX equal
minus P dot how many people remember
minus P dot thank
you everybody remember
that of course you
do okay let's check let's see what we
get d h by DP is equal to X do the H by
DP is p so this says that P equals x dot
right that's not too bad momentum is
equal to Velocity what happened to the
mass oh I said the mass equal to one so
that's okay it's all right I'm a
physicist I'm allowed to do
that P is equal to x dot that's good now
what about the H by the X the H by the x
is Omega
squar
X plus or
minus
minus okay let's check Newton's
equations let's calculate the
acceleration the acceleration is x
dot that's P dot but P dot is equal to
uh P Dot
do I have the sign wrong here d h by
DX = minus P dot = + Omega x^2 the H by
the x is plus Omega
x^2 so x dot is equal to minus Omega 2
x x dot is minus Omega 2 x that's the
equation of an oscillator with frequency
Omega okay everybody recognize
it X do is minus Omega 2
x
acceleration M was set equal to 1
acceleration is equal to restoring
force with as I said K is equal to Omega
squ okay so this is the right
hamiltonian for the harmonic
oscillator and now what we want to do is
find all its energy levels
igen vectors and find out what it does
Quantum mechanically classically we know
what it does it swings back and forth
with frequency
Omega okay let's see what we can do with
it it's the sum of
squares what do you do with the sum of
squares you factor
it everybody knows that you factor the
sum of squares well not everybody knows
that D knew it
all right so let's write first of all a
1/2
downstairs and let's write p + I Omega x
* P - I Omega X is this looking familiar
not from the harmonic oscillator but
from about an hour
ago LX Plus i l y and LX minus i l
y yeah okay so let's do this is this
right
yeah that's right I'm also going to put
uh yeah I'm going to put an Omega
downstairs and an Omega
upstairs only because it's
convention
okay
now let me not put those omegas I'll do
that
later is this right Quantum
mechanically
corre no because there's a term
P * x and x * P but they don't cancel
because X and P don't commute so let's
see so what do I have to subtract here I
have to subtract minus
one2 from
here and then I will
have
I now we have om
Omega we have x * P - P * X
x * P - P * X and I think the I think I
have it
right I've subtracted it because it was
appearing in here in in an unwanted
way so I've subtracted it and now I use
one more thing this is the commutator of
X and P what's the commutator of X and P
I I've dropped H bars all over the place
we'll put back the H
bars
later okay XP minus
PX that's I commutator of P of X with
P equals I strictly i h bar if I wanted
to keep the
um
uh why is that true hm why is that true
you know remember that no from two years
ago
I'll that's the basic economical
commutation relations of a coordinate
and its corresponding
momentum case it's the one dimensional
case yeah one dimensional case it's not
PX no then you have a problem why uh
then it'll be zero hm x commutes with p
y and
pz yeah so this is yeah but this this is
X and PX there's only one coordinate in
this problem that's what I'm saying
that's the one dimensional case you had
the other dimensions you would have to
clarify if you had other dimensions you
have to worry about them you
don't okay this is the onedimensional
harmonic oscillator so what is XP minus
PX all right let's keep the H bar around
for a second uh we'll keep the H bar
around for a second later on we'll drop
it but um uh it's i h - I * I is plus I
so this becomes
plus h Omega /
2 okay this is a constant
this is a
constant what's it called it's got a
name it's called the Zero Point
Energy it's there even when the harmonic
oscillator is in its ground state we're
going to see that even in its ground
state where this is zero everything else
is zero this Still
Remains why is there a ground state
energy well let's um let's ask why is
why does a harmonic oscillator have a
ground state energy why isn't the Energy
Zero
what's the energy of the ground state
classically zero how does it get to be
zero well the ground state is just the
oscillator at rest P equals 0 at
position zero both of these are zero
Quantum mechanically you can't have both
X and P be zero
simultaneously furthermore both of these
are
positive and therefore they can cancel
each other so there's got to be a little
bit of energy in the ground state it's
the Heisenberg uncertainty principle
which tells you that you couldn't have
had zero energy in the ground
state okay but once you know that here
let the hamiltonian is this thing over
here plus a
constant okay let's drw let the constant
may or may not be important but it's
just an additive number every energy
level has an extra H Omega over 2 we're
not going to lose anything terribly
important if we drop
it um I'm going to drop it but later on
we can come back and add it back in as
an overall additive constant in the
energy yeah um can you say anything
further by the fact that it comes out to
be positive instead of
negative okay it couldn't have been
negative because X2 + p s is positive
the energy is X2 + P sare that's a
positive definite operator it can't come
out to be
negative
right all right so let's concentrate on
this thing over
here let's forget where it came
from we forgetting where it came
from and we just want to know what's the
properties of this operator here's a
certain operator it is the hamiltonian
apart from the S I'm going to say it
once more there an additive constant and
now I'm not going to say it again until
I put it back eventually but this is the
hamiltonian okay and we want to
understand what its spectrum is what its
igen vectors are what is its
properties we have two operators it
factorizes very nicely it makes sense to
give these operators names and I'm going
to do something just for future benefit
I'm going to put an Omega up here
and I'm going to put a square root of
Omega down so here's what we're going to
do we're going to put a square root of 2
Omega
downstairs and a square root of 2 Omega
downstairs
here you see what I did I took the two
that was downstairs and I split it
between these two and I took the Omega
which I stuck upstairs and split it
between the two factors
again this is the standard way that even
the classic iCal harmonic oscillator is
often written in this
way we need to give these guys
names pus I Omega X over < TK 2 Omega
and p+ I Omega
X their role is going to be exactly the
same as the raising and lowering
operators in the uh in the angular
momentum case it's going to take us up
and down a
ladder this time it'll be a ladder of
energy levels not a lat of angular
momentum okay so let's give them names
A+ is equal to p + I Omega X over < TK
of 2 Omega and a minus is the same thing
but with a minus IX over < TK of 2
Omega they are hermiss conjugates of
each other they're her mission
conjugates of each
other because one plus I Omega x- I
Omega
X and we can now write that the
hamiltonian is
Omega * A+ a
minus that is really simple except who
knows what's buried in the A+ and the a
minus it's a it's a it's a crappy
looking thing for sure to have square
roots of Omega and square roots of two
but it's turns out not to be so
crappy okay
what what should we do with these a
pluses and a
minuses what what would D
do yeah I do that but uh but probably
stare at it for a while say I can't
figure out the igen
values he would commute them you would
commute them you would say what's the
commutator here I have a hamiltonian
which is A+ a minus I don't know much
about A+ and a minus but let's figure
out what the what their commutator is
I'm bored I've got nothing else to
do I I like this I like to sit around
and commute
things okay so let's let's take the
commutator of a minus with
A+ okay that's going to be
commutator of now there's going to be a
two Omega downstairs right two Omega
downstairs 1 over two
Omega and then there's going to be the
commutator of P minus I Omega
x with p + I Omega
X now who commutes with who here or who
doesn't commute with who who doesn't
commute with
whom all right P doesn't commute with x
and x doesn't commute with P that's all
x commutes with X and P commutes with P
so what do we have here we have equals 1
over 2
Omega now we have an i Omega let's take
this let's
take let's take this one here
first then we have a minus I
Omega minus I omeg GA from here and then
the commutator of X with P what's the
commutator of X with
p i so that gives us an
i i * - I is +
1 we have an Omega over
Omega all together this is just
1/2 but that was only one term
that was this commutator of this one
with this one the other one is the
commutator of p with I Omega X it's
exactly the same if you work it out
you'll see it's exactly the same number
and so all together you get two of
them plus a
half and the commutator is
one we now know two things turns out
this is enough this is really all you
have to know
you can throw away everything
else the hamiltonian is Omega time A+ a
minus and the commutator of a minus with
A+ is 1 there's one more fact here and
it's the fact that A+ and a minus are
herian conjugates of each other that
plays a role
okay
good let's give this thing
a plus a minus by itself a name let's
call it capital
N it even gets simpler now the
commutator of H of H is Omega time
n and the next step of course if we had
if we were direct would be to start
commuting in with A+ and in with a minus
it's a good thing to do it's a good
thing to do you'll find out that the
commutator algebra is very simple but I
don't think we have to do it I think we
we can um
proceed without doing
that let's see what we can
learn first of all this inob is a Herm
Mission operator if you take an operator
times its own hermiss conjugate it's
always hermiss that's something you can
check that means n has a complete set of
igen vectors well of course n is Herm
Mission it's basically apart from the
Factor Omega it's the
hamiltonian it started Herm Mission it
stays Herm
Mission so N is a Herm Mission operator
and that means it has a complete set of
igen values and igen vectors what we
want to do is find those igen values and
igen vectors those igen values and igen
vectors are the energy levels and igen
states of the of the
hamiltonian okay so let's uh let's see
what we can learn we want to find the
igen values of n once we know the igen
values of n we know everything we want
to know so let's suppose that
n has an igen Vector called little
n and that the igen value is just little
N I haven't made any assumptions about
whether little n is an integer or
anything
else I've called it
n because it is an integer but we
haven't we haven't proved that let's
just call it little n Big N is an
operator it's a plus a minus little n is
an igen value this is the igen value
equation okay and we can also write it
in another way we can write it A+ a
minus on little n is little n * n I've
just written that big n is a plus a
minus right these two equations are the
same thing now let's take the
commutation relation here let's write it
out
a minus
A+ minus a A+ a
minus equals
1 but let's take this operator this
equation and operate on the state
n and see what we get
all right you agree with this equation
it's just a commutation relation a minus
A+ a plus a minus equal 1 but then
hus what's
that thank
you
yeah
good and let's multiply it
I'm looking at I'm staring at it trying
to figure out what to do with it I know
what I really want to do with it what I
want to do with it is I want to apply A+
what I want to do is show that A+ will
increase the energy I want to show that
A+ is a raising
operator so what I want I want to
concentrate not on N but on A+ time
n so I have to multiply it by A+
this is my goal to show that A+ * n is
something interesting that raising with
this A+ operator does something
interesting okay so now we have an
equation let's see what we get
um first of all we have A+ a
minus A+ that's the first term here on
N now what about the second term
minus
A+ ah
what's A+ a minus on
N right so this is minus A+ minus
n A+ *
n I've written that a plus a minus on N
just gives me a numerical Factor n so
that's this over here I still have the
A+ and that's over
here and finally on the right hand side
I have a + *
n
okay let's shift this over to the right
what happens if I shift this over to the
right here I have A+ * n and here I have
n * A+ *
n what do I
get n + 1 oo that's good
let's see this one got shifted over to
the right it gave me this n and the
other one gave me the one but what about
this one over
here A + * a
minus is the operator capital
N this is the state that I'm interested
in so n on this state A+ on N let's put
a circle around it is equal
to n + 1 times that same
state so guess what I found pretty much
what was expected that the raising
operator gives me a new igen Vector of
capital N with an igen value one unit
up okay so here's what what we found
pictorially if I plot on the vertical
axis here the igen values of
n then if I find
one little
n then there's another one above it and
another one above it and another one
above it unless of course I run out but
we're going to prove that we can't run
out there's another one above it and
another one above
it each
one being shifted by one
unit n n n plus1 n plus2 and so forth so
if I find a solution an igen value n
there'll be another one at n+1 there'll
be another one at n+ 2 another one at n+
3 and furthermore you go from one to the
other by applying the operator
A+ A+ takes you from an igen Vector with
igen value n to an igen value n+ one and
so
forth these of course have higher and
higher energy because the energy is just
Omega time
n what about going
down how do you go down what's the thing
that takes you
down a minus so it's a straightforward
thing to prove that um same deal
that a minus on N takes you
down how far down can it take you can it
take
you indefinitely
down why
not because the harmonic oscillat
hamiltonian is
positive
it's only got positive terms you cannot
get to negative values the operator is a
positive definite operator which means
it only has um positive igen values in
fact it's a theorem that if you multiply
an operator by its own conjugate by its
own Herm Mission conjugate its igen
values are positive or at worse zero or
at worse zero so it can't go
indefinitely down there's got to be
a last
one that last one is called the ground
state and it's usually labeled o
you can't go indefinitely down what does
that mean what takes you down is a minus
so a minus on N takes you to n + one n
minus one or it takes you to
zero or it just kills a state so there's
nothing below it those are the only two
mathematical possibilities a minus takes
you down or you just run out of states
there are no States below it that's what
what happens a
minus on
O is just zero so there's nothing down
below n equal Z the first the first
state corresponds to n equal 0 n equals
z question yeah uh if if we take n and
we apply a minus get to nus one and then
if we apply a plus to that
n yeah but then A+ Aus * n is n * n
let's do it
again the of a plus a minus is n rather
than one so if we're app a minus and
then a
plus is that one or n okay so let's be
careful Let's
uh I've been a little bit careless I've
written that
A+ on n is equal to n + 1 but I haven't
discussed the normalization of these
states the normalization of these states
is
not n
m equals Delta n
m there's a numerical Factor there's a
numerical
factor and if we wanted to keep track of
that numerical
Factor I'm quite tired now and I think
we have have to quit but there is a
square root of n + 1
here * n + 1 now try your trick again
and see what you
get and I think it's also true that a
minus on N I think gives you square otk
of n * n minus1 if I'm not
mistaken I think that's
correct now what do you want to do you
want to try
you want to try a + * a
minus on
N was that the was that the game
somebody asked me okay let's see what we
get all right A minus on N gives
me we're going to have A+ then we're
going to have square < TK of n
nus1 now what happens when
A+ hits n minus one
here it gives me another square root of
n so this gives me two factors of square
root of n *
n so I was a little bit
sloppy I didn't tell you what the
normalization of the states were the
states are not normalized uh by by that
I mean they're not uh chronica Delta
normalized then normalized to some weird
factors with square roots of n andm uh
when we need that and we will need it
we'll we'll write it down but I
um I was uh it's getting a little too
late to for all possible
details okay yeah oh incidentally yeah
just one point um notice that this
equation here says that when a minus
hits the ground state it does give
zero yeah
uh does the ground state have to be zero
or can it be above zero above zero what
well no it has to be zero it has to be
zero is that clear why it has to be zero
well here yeah
um
uh yeah that's let's
see
um well is Z yeah Vector is ifus one is
zero
Z we can prove it I'm a little bit tired
now and I don't know what the proof uh
proof is but that's a good question uh
it is the answer is zero the answer is
that the spectrum of capital N here is
all of the integers starting at
zero okay so that tells us that the
energy spectrum is Omega times an
integer there is an har bar in here and
I'll I'll go through the H bars I'll
tell you where the H bars are hiding
next time but um it tells you that the
energy spectrum is Omega times an
integer
plus the famous 1/2 har bar Omega that
we threw
away so there's the ground state Energy
Plus on top of it the spectrum of
integer space levels that's the harmonic
oscillator and
um we'll play with bit more but more
important we'll use it to solve some
important problems
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu